Guide to the Joseph P. Breedlove papers, 1913-1950
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Joseph P. Breedlove papers 1913-1950
University Archives, Duke University
Breedlove, Joseph Penn, 1874-1955
2.0 Linear Feet 2000 Items
Breedlove was appointed Librarian of Trinity College in 1898 and oversaw the growth of the libraries after Trinity expanded to become Duke University. He served as Librarian until 1939 when he was named Librarian Emeritus.
The Joseph P. Breedlove papers document the expansion and management of the Duke University Library after the General Library opens in 1930. The papers contain some annual reports of the Trinity College as well as an undated Guide to the Trinity College Library. Correspondence with Library Council member B. Harvie Branscomb includes a June 14, 1937 feasibility report of the resources needed to convert the Library classification scheme from Dewey Decimal to Library of Congress. The collection also includes a history of Wiley Gray medal with a list of winners.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Joseph P. Breedlove papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1955-1974.
Biographical Note
Joseph P. Breedlove was born July 15, 1874 in Granville, N.C., to John Henry and Susan Caroline Breedlove. A descendant of John Penn, one of North Carolina's signers of the Declaration of Independence, Breedlove attended Horner's Military School in Oxford, N.C. He went on to the University of North Carolina in 1894, but transferred after his freshman year to Trinity College, where he received his undergraduate degree in 1898 and a Masters of Arts degree in 1902.
Breedlove was appointed Librarian of Trinity College in September of 1898, when the Library occupied a single room in the Washington Duke Building. Breedlove received his Library training in the summer of 1900 at Amherst, where he studied under William I. Fletcher, who was a pioneer in the field of library education. While at Amherst he also met Charles A. Cutter, who developed the Cutter classification system. Breedlove continued his library education in the summer of 1902, when he did a practicum at the Enoch Pratt Free Library in Baltimore.
By 1902 the Trinity College Library had grown to 15,000 volumes and moved to the newly completed Library over the Christmas break. Until September of 1914 when he was able to hire a staff member to assist with cataloging, Breedlove handled all aspects of Library operation with minimal student assistance. Library operations grew substantially after Trinity College expanded into Duke University. During the period of 1924 to 1930, Library operations grew to include the General Library (West campus) and the Woman's College Library (East campus) as well as the libraries for the schools of Law, Medicine, and Religion. Under Breedlove's direction, the General Library was organized into the divisions of Reference, Circulation, Periodicals, Newspaper, Serials, and Continuations, Reserve Books, and Graduate Reserve as well as the departments of Catalog, Order, and Manuscript.
Breedlove served as Librarian until September 1939 when he was named Librarian Emeritus. In the years after his retirement he continued to work on library projects and wrote a history of the Library entitled Duke University Library, 1840-1940.
Collection Overview
The bulk of the Breedlove papers document the expansion and management of the Library after the General Library opens in 1930. Some annual reports from the Trinity College era can be found in Box 1 and an undated Guide to the Trinity College Library is located in Box 3. Box 3 also contains speeches and articles by Breedlove as well as a report on library instruction for freshmen. Of particular interest is a folder in Box 1 containing Breedlove’s correspondence with B. Harvie Branscomb. Branscomb was a member of the Library Council and served as Director of Libraries (a faculty appointment) from 1934 to 1941. A June 14, 1937 feasibility report of the resources needed to convert the Library classification scheme from Dewey Decimal to Library of Congress can be found in the Branscomb folder. In addition to materials about the Library, the collection also includes documentation of Breedlove’s campus activities with the Trinity Class of 1898 and a history of Wiley Gray medal with a list of winners.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Branscomb, Bennett Harvie, 1894 -
Breedlove, Joseph Penn, 1874-1955
Classification -- Books
Duke University. Library
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Library
Wiley Gray Medal
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Annual report of the Library, 1913-1925 (Box 1)
  - Annual report of the Library, 1928-1935
  - Annual report of the Library, 1944-1945
  - Binding, 1929-1933
  - Book loans, 1934-1942
  - Books lost, 1938-1946
  - Branscomb, Harvie, correspondence and reports, 1927-1940
  - Budget fund, 1925-1927
  - Church material in Duke Library, 1941-1943
  - Class of 1898 alumni file
  - Correspondence, 1923-1924
  - Correspondence, 1924-1927
  - Correspondence, 1928-1933
  - Correspondence, 1934-1938 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1941
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943
  - Correspondence, 1944-1949
  - Correspondence, personnel, 1925-1942
  - Correspondence, student assistants, 1927-1942
  - Equipment, 1931-1935
  - Expenditures, 1929
  - Fee fund and reports, 1930-1942
  - Financial reports, 1920-1929
  - Friends of the Duke University Library, 1945
  - Glasson, William, 1924-1942
  - Guide to the Use of the Trinity College Library (Box 3)
  - Inventory and reference survey, 1934-1935
  - John Spencer Bassett Collection contributions
  - Library Committee/Council, 1920-1942
  - Medicine, 1926
  - Memos, receipts, miscellaneous, 1929-1950
  - N.Y.A. workers, 1934-1942 (2 folders)
  - North Carolina Library Association, 1933-1946
  - Periodicals received, 1931-1946
  - Red Cross British War Relief, 1941-1942
  - Report on Library Instruction for Freshmen, 1937-1938
  - Report to the American Library Association, 1932-1938
  - Speeches and writings
  - Staff of the General Library, 1928-1940 (Box 4)
  - Staff salaries, 1931-1939
  - Statistics, 1930-1941
  - Statistics, accessions, 1931-1946
  - Statistics, manuscripts, 1934-1940
  - Statistics, Trinity and Duke, 1882-1929
  - Student help, 1939-1942
  - Treasure Room lists, 1931-1932
  - Wiley Gray Medals winners and history, 1879-1942